[Music]
hey what's up guys my name is Chen oh
welcome back to my c++ series today
we're gonna be talking all about threads
and in general how we can parallel eyes
that's a hard word how we can make stuff
happen in parallel because most of the
computers or processes or devices that
we're programming for nowadays have more
than one logical thread of processing
that they can actually do so far all the
code that we've been writing in the c++
series and the opengl series as well if
you guys are watching that has been on a
single thread which means that when we
actually write code for those episodes
and for those series we're literally
just making the computer do things one
kind of line of code at a time on one
instruction at a time which is fine a
lot of the things that we've written
have obviously not been particularly
fast or that they haven't needed to be
really like well optimized or really
quick because we haven't really written
any heavy code any code that has that
will actually take the device a long
time to compute it's been really simple
stuff but as we get into more complex
programs it's very beneficial for us to
actually move off certain work to
different threads of execution not just
for the sake of kind of performance but
also for the sake of what we can
actually do with that for example we've
used sed CN get to request input from
the user into the console however we
can't do anything while we're waiting
for input can we we're literally just
waiting to receive input and that's kind
of like a while true loop that's just
going on infinitely and until we press
ENTER that's it like our thread is
blocked but what if we could maybe do
something else like print something to
the console or just log something or
write a file or whatever while we're
actually waiting for user input we still
want other things to happen that's one
example that's probably really simple to
understand but anyway we're just gonna
dive right into the code and see what we
can actually do alright so the first
thing I'm going to do is show you kind
of how threads work on what we can do
with them so I'm going to include this
thread header that we have here which
includes the threading support basically
into this file so that we can use a
thread class and everything and I type
in sed thread I'm gonna call it
something so I'll call this a work
because it's gonna be like our worker
thread and then what I mean what are you
to do is pass in a function and
optionally any kind of arguments that it
may need so let's make a function called
do work this is going to be the word
this is going to be the function that
actually performs what we want to happen
on another thread of execution so I'm
going to pass it into here by just
typing and do work if you guys haven't
seen my function pointers video
definitely check that up because this is
how this works it takes in a function
pointer that's why we just pass in do
work without parentheses or anything
like that video link will be up there
and as soon as we write this actual code
it's going to immediately kick off that
thread and it's going to do whatever is
in here and it's going to keep running
until we wait for it to exit so the way
that we can actually wait for something
to finish or wait for a thread to
complete its work is by tacking is by
typing in worker dot join so this is our
thread object of course and then this
join function is essentially going to
just wait for this thread to be joined
now thread joining is a another kind of
portent potentially complex topic that
might be worth discussing in more detail
but basically in like in c-sharp and
kind of more modern programming it's
just called wait or wait for exit or
just me away it is probably reasonable
basically all of this does is it just
says hey can you wait on the current
thread for this thread to finish its
work so block the current thread until
this other thread has completed so
because this stuff is running in
parallel we have our main thread which
starts off a worker thread which does
its work and then eventually what we're
doing by writing this join kind of call
here is we're saying on the main thread
wait for that worker thread to finish
all of its execution before we continue
on was with whatever our main thread
hands so what that means is that this CN
dot get line of code will not run
because it's the next line of code after
this it will not run until everything
that is in this function has finished
and we'll say this in pro and prayer
will citizen practice in just a second
as well so as an example what I'm going
to do now is just let's just dive right
into it and I'll demonstrate that
example that I made with sand cat if we
just write a normal program maybe we
want work to be done that prints
something to the console we'll say it
prints working to
council just like that and it's going to
kind of keep running forever we
essentially wanted to just run forever
so I'll put this into here if we were to
want to write something like this that
performs any kind of work that happens
until we tell it to stop by maybe
hitting enter how would we go about
doing this well we know that what we
could do is we could say Manuela Casey
and don't get so maybe we want this
while loop to continue until saying get
actually return something because saying
get we'll just wait for us to basically
press Enter so we want to write a
program that waits until we press ENTER
but the line of code that waits until we
press Enter
blocks execution because it's waiting
for us to press ENTER so it can't
actually print working continuously
because it's waiting for us to press
ENTER so on one thread this doesn't
really work we need to be able to do two
things at the same time we want to be
able to wait for the user to press ENTER
and repeatedly check to see has the user
press ENTER but then we also want to log
working to the console so let's look at
one way that we might solve this so what
I'm going to do is write a static
boolean here called s working and or
well we'll call it s finished and I'll
set it equal to false because we haven't
finished yet and then this while loop
will run until finished has been set to
true so while not finished keep printing
out working and then what I'm going to
do over here is Pesta D syndicate which
blocks this thread until we press ENTER
and after we press ENTER I'm on a set
finish to true and then I'm gonna go
just wait for this work at thread to
join so what's happening here if we look
at this kind of concurrently and how
it's actually running this is printing
working as fast as I can to the console
and that's all it's doing this thread is
waiting for us to press the Enter key
and when we do in advances to line 19
which that's finished it true the next
time this checks checks the state of
finished it will see that it's been set
to true which means that I'm finished so
it's going to advance past this while
loop and at the end of the function thus
that thread has finished and this is
going to make sure that we don't do see
and get until that thread
has actually finished its execution so
if we just hit f5 and say what this
actually does you can see over here that
is repeatedly printing walking and when
I press ENTER that's it it stops
printing working and if I press ENTER
again it's going to terminate our
program because we have another scene
not get over here which waits for that
before it just closes our program sorry
maybe instead of printing working as
fast as possible we might want to say
well actually let's wait for a bit
the thing with multi-threading is that
if you continually do things as fast as
possible like this it is going to kind
of result in like a hundred percent CPU
usage for that thread which isn't great
so what we can do is because they will
wait for a bit and what I'm going to do
here is just tell this current thread to
sleep so I'm going to write asleep
before and then one s which stands for
one second and in order to write code
like that I'm gonna have to using
namespace Pro know literals okay so
basically I'm just saying after you
print this working line of code just
sleep for a second before you go back up
to this while loop and continue printing
working until finished is set to true so
if I hit f5 now we should get working
printing to the console once every
second and there we go you can see that
it's ticking like that working working
and if I press ENTER then that's it it's
done and in fact let's just maybe write
something to just indicate that it's
done so after work adjoin I'll print
finished and let's see what that looks
like so there we go working working
working ENTER and you can see we've
finished and that is the end of our
execution so that's a very basic example
of how threads work arguably fairly
useless but the point of this video is
just to show you first of all how you
can access threads in the C++ API
of course this ends up boiling down to
platform specific code but you just need
to include thread and when you just make
a thread object by typing in a city
thread and then you make a variable out
of it and you pass in a function to the
constructor that immediately kicks off
that thread doing whatever work you've
made it to and that thread will continue
until it's done you can always use like
that thread join to actually wait for
the current thread that's kicked off
that second thread to actually finish
its execution in case you need to do
some kind of clean up or wait like this
for the actual program to terminate
after all the threads are done that's as
far as the API goes there's really not a
lot of things you can do there's not a
lot of things you need to do the concept
of threads is really really simple but
it gets really complicated really
quickly like a lot of things do in C++
the sed this thread thing as well can
just make sure well there's also a this
thread object that I used here if I just
grab my laptop again we have this sed
this thread which you can use to
actually basically give commands to the
current thread because you can say that
in this thread I don't have access to
this thread object even though I'm
actually on it so what I could do for
example is just print the thread ID that
I'm on so I might say something like s
CDCR
started thread ID equals and then I'll
print the actual thread ID by typing in
a city this thread get ID and then I'll
copy that line of code and also print it
maybe after we finish over here and
these authorities should be different
because they're running on different
threads so if I hit f5 to run my program
you can see we start at thread ID 8 3 4
8 and then if I hit enter you can see
it's a completely different ID because
they're actually on different threads of
execution we've created another thread
to print our working stuff to the
console so yeah threads are really
important we're going to be talking a
lot more about them in the future
they're really useful for speeding up
your program the primary purpose of
threads is optimisation but not only you
can also use them to do things like we
did today that isn't really possible to
do because we literally need to be able
to do two things at once
if you did have your own send dog gate
function you could of course alternate
between work what I mean by that is
let's see if the users press ENTER if
not let's print working to the console
then we do that again like you can do it
on one thread you can't with seen yet
because it blocks the entire thread but
if you had your own method there's no
reason why you couldn't do that so it's
not like things are completely
impossible it's just more or less than
some things a lot easier and a lot
faster if you actually utilize threading
and that's a huge topic which we will
continue to explore in the future do you
guys like this video you can hit the
like button you can also help support
this series by go to patreon.com/scishow
no link will be in the description huge
thank you as always to all the patron
support this series they would not be
here without you I'm gonna get out of
this forest before it gets too dark and
I'll see you guys next time goodbye
[Music]